Matthew Bernhard

Ph.D. Candidate, Computer Science and Engineering University of Michigan

December 3, 2019

2260 Hayward Street Ann Arbor, MI 48109 USA matber@umich.edu

mbernhard.com

Research Overview

My research focuses on areas where the security and privacy implications of sophisticated systems impacts users in the real world. My interests include election security, usability, human-computer interaction, censorship measurement and resistance, Internet measurement, cryptography, statistics, and systems security. I'm also interested in the intersection of computer science, psychology, politics, and policy.

Education

- Ph.D in Computer Science, University of Michigan, Expected Spring 2021
 Advisor: J. Alex Halderman
- M.S. in Computer Science, University of Michigan, Summer 2018
- B.A. in Computer Science, Rice University, Spring 2015
 Advisor: Dan S. Wallach

Refereed Conference Publications

[1] Decentralized Control: A Case Study of Russia

Reethika Ramesh, Ram Sundara Raman, <u>Matthew Bernhard</u>, Victor Ongkowijaya, Leonid Evdokimov, Anne Edmundson, Steven Sprecher, Muhammad Ikram, Roya Ensafi To appear in *Proceedings of the 27th Network and Distributed Systems Symposium* (NDSS'20), February 2020.

[2] UnclearBallot: Automated Ballot Image Manipulation

<u>Matthew Bernhard</u>, Kartikeya Kandula, Jeremy Wink, and J. A. Halderman In *Proceedings of the 4th International Joint Conference on Electronic Voting* (E-Vote-ID'19), October 2019.

[3] On the Usability of HTTPS Deployment

<u>Matthew Bernhard</u>, Jonathan Sharman, Claudia Ziegler Acemyan, Philip Kortum, Dan S. Wallach, and J. A. Halderman

In Proceedings of the ACM Conference on Human Factors on Computing Systems (CHI'19), May 2019.

[4] 403 Forbidden: A Global View of CDN Geoblocking

Allison McDonald, <u>Matthew Bernhard</u>, Luke Valenta, Benjamin VanderSloot, Will Scott, Nick Sullivan, J. A. Halderman, Roya Ensafi In *Proceedings of the ACM Internet Measurement Conference* (IMC'18), November 2018.

[5] Public Evidence from Secret Ballots

<u>Matthew Bernhard</u>, Josh Benaloh, J. A. Halderman, Ronald L. Rivest, Peter Y. A. Ryan, Philip B. Stark, Vanessa Teague, Poorvi L. Vora, and Dan S. Wallach
In *Proceedings of the 2nd International Joint Conference on Electronic Voting*(E-Vote-ID'17), October 2017.

[6] Understanding the Mirai Botnet

Manos Antonakakis, Tim April, Michael Bailey, <u>Matthew Bernhard</u>, Elie Bursztein, Jaime Cochran, Zakir Durumeric, J. A. Halderman, Luca Invernizzi, Michalis Kallitsis, Deepak Kumar, Chaz Lever, Zane Ma, Joshua Mason, Damian Menscher, Chad Seaman, Nick Sullivan, Kurt Thomas, and Yi Zhou

In Proceedings of the 26th USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX'17), August 2017.

[7] Implementing Attestable Kiosks

Matthew Bernhard, J. A. Halderman, and Gabe Stocco In Proceedings of the 14th IEEE Conference on Privacy, Security, and Trust (PST'16), December 2016.

[8] Towards a Complete View of the Certificate Ecosystem

Benjamin VanderSloot, Johanna Amann, <u>Matthew Bernhard</u>, Zakir Durumeric, Michael Bailey, J. A. Halderman

In Proceedings of the ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC'16), November 2016.

Refereed Workshop Publications

[9] Bernoulli Ballot-Polling: A Manifest Improvement for Risk-Limiting Audits

Kellie Ottoboni, <u>Matthew Bernhard</u>, J. A. Halderman, Ronald L. Rivest, and Philip B. Stark In *Proceedings of the 4th Annual Workshop on Advances in Secure Electronic Voting* (Voting'19), February 2019.

[10] Voting Technologies, Recount Methods and Votes in Wisconsin and Michigan in 2016

Walter R. Mebane, Jr., Matthew Bernhard

In Proceedings of the 3rd Annual Workshop on Advances in Secure Electronic Voting (Voting'18), February 2019.

Selected Other Publications

[11] The Security Challenges of Online Voting Have Not Gone Away

Robert Cunningham, <u>Matthew Bernhard</u>, J. A. Halderman In *IEEE Spectrum*, November 2016.

Speaking

Major Invited Talks and Keynotes

- Recount 2016 and Student Voter Engagement

University of Pennsylvania Voter Engagement Week, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, September 2019.

- U.S. Civil Rights Commission testimony on voter registration security

Michigan Advisory Committee to the U.S. Commission on Civil Rights, Detroit, Michigan, April 2019.

- Panel: Next Generation Voting Systems (moderator)

Election Verification Network Conference, Washington, D.C., March 2019.

- Panel: Usability and Voter Verification (moderator)

Election Verification Network Conference, Washington, D.C., March 2019.

- A Crash Course on Election Security

2018 DEF CON Voting Village, Las Vegas, Nevada, August 2018.

- Panel: Do We Want a Recount or Not?

Election Verification Network Conference, Washington, D.C., March 2017.

– Recount 2016: An Uninvited Security Audit of the U.S. Presidential Election

2017 RoadSec, São Paulo, Brazil, November 2017.

- Recount 2016: An Uninvited Security Audit of the U.S. Presidential Election

33rd Chaos Communications Congress, Hamburg, Germany, December 2016.

Selected Talks

Cybersecurity and U.S. Elections

Invited speaker, RoadSec Pro, São Paulo, Brazil, November 2017; Invited speaker, Workshop on Electoral Technologies, Brasilia, Brazil, June 2017;

- Internet Pinball: The Security and Privacy Impact of Redirects

Mozilla Security Research Summit, San Francisco, California, May 2019.

- Election Security and You

Midwest Security Workshop, Chicago, Illinois, April 2019.

- Coercion-resistant, Receipt-free, and Paperless Voting

Rump session at Financial Cryptography and Data Security 2019, St. Kitts, February 2019.

- 403 Forbidden: A Global View of Geoblocking

Rump session, 9th USENIX Workshop on Free and Open Communications on the Internet (FOCI'18), Baltimore, Maryland, August 2018.

- A Constitutional Argument Against Burr-Feinstein

Rump session, 25th USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX'16), Austin, Texas, August 2017.

Advising and Mentoring

Undergraduate Independent Work

– 2019: Henry Meng, Jensen Hwa, Thea Lau, Chand Rajendra-Nicolucci, Antonio Atkinson, Jeremy Wink, Kartikey Kandula

Teaching

- Graduate Student Instructor, Election Cybersecurity (Fall 2018)

EECS 498, University of Michigan

Assisted with design and teaching of an undergraduate research course into election security. Lectured, wrote homework assignments, and oversaw ten undergraduate independent research projects.

- Graduate Student Instructor, Introduction to Computer Security (Winter 2018)

EECS 388, University of Michigan

Led discussion section, wrote and graded assignments, and lectured.

- Course Operations Liaison, Securing Digital Democracy (2014-2018)

Coursera (MOOC), University of Michigan

Assisted with content maintenance and day-to-day course operations for a massive, open online course about electronic voting and Internet voting technologies.

- Teaching Assistant, Fundamentals of Parallel Programming (Spring 2015)

COMP 322, Rice University

Shaped curriculum and led lab discussions for a introductory course on parallel programming featuring Java parallelism and Apache Spark

- Teaching Assistant, Introduction to Program Design (Fall 2014)

COMP 215, Rice University

Led lab discussions and wrote and reviewed assignments and exams for an introductory course on Java and Object Oriented Programming

Professional Service

Program Committee

- Program co-chair, 6th Workshop on Advances in Secure Electronic Voting (Voting'21)
- Program co-chair, 5th Workshop on Advances in Secure Electronic Voting (Voting'20)

External Reviewer

- ACM Conferences on Human Factors in Computing Systems (CHI'20)
- USENIX Security Symposium (USENIX'19)
- ACM Internet Measurement Conference (IMC'18)
- ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS'18)
- International Symposium on Research in Attacks, Intrusions, and Defenses (RAID'18)
- ACM Conference on Computer and Communications Security (CCS'17)
- Network and Distributed System Security Symposium (NDSS'17)
- IEEE Conference on Privacy, Security, and Trust (PST'16)

Broader Impact of Selected Projects

- Implementing Better Election Security (2018–2019)

Currently working with the State of Michigan and municipalities across the state to pilot risk-limiting audits to help secure Michigan's elections. Developed software that interfaces with voting technology to enable ballot comparison audits.

- Fighting Weak IoT Security (2017)

Applied machine learning techniques to Internet measurement data to identify make and model of consumer devices that were infected by the Mirai botnet. Data has been used in ongoing legal proceedings by the Federal Trade Commission to encourage U.S. manufacturers to improve the default security of their devices.

- 2016 U.S. Presidential Election Recounts (2016)

Supported efforts to detect vote manipulation in the 2016 election in Michigan, Wisconsin, and Pennsylvania. While progress was hindered and in places entirely halted due to political and legal reasons, what little evidence htat was generated did not show that the 2016 Presidential election was fraudulent.

Professional Experience

Expert Witness (2018–present)

Served as an expert witness in several lawsuits opposing the use of direct-recording electronic voting machines. Curling et al. v. Raffensperger, CGG v. Crittenden, Shelby Advocates for Valid Elections et al. v. Hargett et al.

- Software Engineering Consultant for VotingWorks (June 2020–present)
 Implemented risk-limiting audit math for VotingWorks' open source risk-limiting audit tool Arlo.
- Data Science Consultant for Verified Voting (June 2018–September 2019)
 Collected and interpreted data on currently certified voting equipment in the United States to empower municipalities to make intelligent purchasing decisions. Focus on the cyber security impacts of voting technology.
- Cryptography Intern, Cloudflare (2017)

Developed Certificate Transparency monitoring features. Also built an SSL detector to determine what SSL settings customer sites can support, under the advising of Nick Sullivan.

- Microsoft Research Intern (2015)

Explored applications of trusted platform modules (TPMs) in voting through interfaces provided by Windows 10 under the advising of Josh Benaloh.